Guide to the Office of Institutional Advancement Records, 1958-1981 UA.11.01.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Office of Institutional Advancement records
1958-1981.
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Office of Institutional Advancement
UA.11.01.0001
1 Linear Feet
The Office of Institutional Advancement was created in 1961 to organize public and alumni relations, fund raising, and long-range planning and development at Duke University. The collection features addresses by E. H. Hopkins, the first Vice President for Institutional Advancement; reference files concerning the administration and history of the Office of Institutional Advancement; reports and studies focusing on fundraising and development of Duke University; and the Office's subject files. Major subjects include planned giving, the Fifth Decade campaign, and corporate support. In 1981, the Office of Institutional Advancement was eliminated and its duties largely assumed by the Office of University Development. English.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the director of the office of use and the University Archivist is required for use.
Provenance
Received from the Office of Institutional Advancement, 1964, 1976, 1983, 1995.
Historical Note
Everett H. Hopkins was appointed Vice President for Institutional Advancement in January 1961 and began his duties in July of that year. The Long-Range Planning Committee of the late 1950s and early 1960s demonstrated the need for organized institutional advancement and large-scale development. Originally, the Vice President for Institutional Advancement was responsible for all public and alumni relations, fund raising, and long-range planning and development. In 1963, long-range planning duties were separated from Institutional Advancement and a new office was created. Hopkins became Vice President for Planning and Institutional Studies. By 1970, offices that fell under Institutional Advancement included Development, Placement Services, Public Relations, and University Editor. In the spring of 1981, President Sanford wanted to redefine the office and its duties. As a result, the Institutional Advancement office was eliminated and its duties largely fell under the office of University Development. The Institutional Advancement program was led by Everett H. Hopkins (1961-1963); Frank L. Ashmore (1963-1973); J. David Ross (1973-1979); and Marion B. Peavey (1979-1981, served as Director; Vice Presidency unfilled after Ross).
Scope and Content Note
The collection features addresses by E. H. Hopkins, the first Vice President for Institutional Advancement; reference files concerning the administration and history of the Office of Institutional Advancement; reports and studies focusing on fundraising and development of Duke University; and the Office's subject files. Major subjects include planned giving and corporate support.
Universities and colleges -- North Carolina -- Finance; Deferred giving; Educational fund raising -- United States; Institutional advancement; Hopkins, Everett H., 1912-; Duke University. Office of Institutional Advancement; Duke University. Office of Institutional Advancement; Duke University -- Finance
- Addresses, 1961 and 1963.
  Scope and Contents note
  Three addresses delivered by Everett H. Hopkins explaining the need for and importance of institutional advancement at Duke. Hopkins gave the first address to the Duke Faculty Club, dated March 21, 1961, before he actually began his duties as Vice President. The series is useful in explaining some of the concepts behind institutional advancement in higher education and its relationship to long-term planning, and showing the importance placed on planning and development at Duke during the early 1960s.
  - A Philosophy of Institutional Advancement, E. H. Hopkins to Duke University Faculty Club. March 21, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Institutional Advancement and the Woman's College, E. H. Hopkins to Woman's College Alumnae luncheon. March 16, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Advancement of Duke University, E. H. Hopkins to Durham Rotary Club. June 10, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Reference files, [1958-1975]
  Two folders of reference or background information on the institution's history and administration, likely kept for use in reports or general reference. Items of note include biographical sketches of major administrative officials, c1963. Also included is a "Student's Guide to the Duke Faculty" -- a who's who of the faculty with an overview of grading and lecture styles, course requirements, and whether the professor is recommended (no date, probably early 1960s).
  - Administration and faculty, [1960-1965] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - History of the University, [1958-1975] (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Reports and Studies, 1961-1963.
  Primarily internal reports documenting the activities of the Institutional Advancement office during its early years under Hopkins. Included are annual reports, calendars of projects and events, and a collection of reports and addresses on each branch of Institutional Advancement at a 1962 staff conference.
  - Annual Report of Vice President for Institutional Advancement, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Three Informal Reports to the Board of Trustees of Duke University, June 2, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Ford Foundation Special Program in Education, August 15, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Institutional Advancement Staff Reports (from Staff Conference), September 25-27, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Corporate Support for Duke: A Case Statement (draft), April 1963 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Analysis and Appraisal of Communications by the Barton Gillet Company, April 1963 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Preliminary Calendar of Projected Programs and Events, 1963-1964, 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Printed reports (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Untitled, incomplete report: Things to do for IA departments, No date (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Subject files, 1961-1979.
  Subject files kept by Hopkins and his successors. Subjects primarily include Estate Planning, the Fifth Decade campaign, and Planned Giving. The bulk of the series dates to the late 1970s when David Ross served as Vice President for Institutional Advancement. Includes self-studies and a 1981 report on Institutional Advancement and Alumni Affairs by a task force of the Associated Students of Duke University.
  - Estate Planning Conference (Duke), October 1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Fifth Decade -- assumptions and projections, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Fifth Decade -- reports and printed material, 1962-1966 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, President Deryl Hart, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Organization, 1961-1976 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Includes correspondence related to the organization of and need for the Office of Institutional Advancement.
  - Organization, 1976-1981 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Includes self-studies and reports on the Office of Institutional Advancement.
  - Office of Planned Giving, October 1979 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - IA Staff Meetings, 1961-1962 and 1976 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Committee of Benefits and Trusts, Handbook, 1979 [addition to records] (Box 1, Folder 23)